I'm Amy Goodman with Narin Sh.
>> A retired CIA agent who blew the whistle
on the AY's Bush era torture program has
been sentenced to two and a half years
in prison. John Kiryaku becomes the
first CIA official to be jailed for any
reason relating to the torture program.
Under a plea deal, Kiyaku admitted to a
single count of violating the
Intelligence Identities Protection Act
by revealing the identity of a covert
officer to a freelance reporter who did
not publish it. Under the plea deal,
prosecutors dropped charges brought
under the Espionage Act. In 2007,
Kiryaku became the first CIA official to
publicly confirm and detail the Bush
administration's use of waterboarding
when he spoke to ABC's Brian Ross. At
the time, I I felt that water boarding
was something that we needed to do. And
as time has passed and has as September
11th has has, you know, has moved
farther and farther back into history,
um I think I've changed my mind. And I
think that waterboarding is probably
something that we shouldn't be in the
business of doing.
>> Why do you say that now?
>> Because we're Americans and we're better
than that.
John Kiryaku supporters say he has been
unfairly targeted in the Obama
administration's crackdown on government
whistleblowers. In a statement urging
President Obama to commute Kiryaku's
sentence, a group of signitaries,
including attorneys and former CIA
officers said, quote, "Kiyaku is an
anti-torrture whistleblower who spoke
out against torture because he believed
it violated his oath to the
Constitution. Please, Mr. President, do
not allow your legacy to be one where
only the whistleblower goes to jail.
Prosecutor Neil McBride, the US Attorney
for the Eastern District of Virginia,
defended the government's handling of
the case. As the judge just said uh in
court,
today's sentence should be a reminder to
every individual who works for the
government who comes into the possession
of closely held sensitive information
regarding the national uh defense or the
identity of a covert agent. uh that it
is critical that that information uh
remain secure and not spill out uh into
the public domain or be shared with
others who don't have uh authorized
access to it.
>> John Kuryaku joins us now from
Washington DC. Spent 14 years at the CIA
as an analyst and a case officer. In
2002, he led the team that found Abu
Zubeda, a high ranking member of
al-Qaeda. He's father of five. In 2010,
he published a memoir entitled The
Reluctant Spy: My Secret Life in the
CIA's War on Terror. And we're joined by
one of John Kuryaku's attorneys,
Jesseline Raak. She's the director of
national security and human rights at
the Government Accountability Project, a
former ethics adviser to the United
States Department of Justice. We reached
out to the US Attorney's Office for the
Eastern District of Virginia, but they
declined our request for an interview.
John Kuryaku, why are you going to jail?
explain the plea deal you made with the
government.
>> Well, thanks first of all for having me
uh and giving me the opportunity to uh
to explain. Uh I'm going to prison uh
ostensibly for violating the
Intelligence Identities Protection Act
of 1982. Uh I believe and my supporters
believe that this however was not a case
about leaking. This was a case about
torture. And I believe I'm going to
prison because I blew the whistle on
torture. I've been a thorn in the CIA
side since that interview in 2007 in
which I said that waterboarding was
torture and that it was official US
government policy. And I think finally
the justice department caught up with
me.
>> Uh Jesseline Raak, let me just bring you
into the conversation to explain what
the Intelligence Identities Protection
Act is. Um your client John Kiryaku uh
it's been invoked in his case for the
first time in 27 years.
That's correct. In fact, there have only
been two convictions under the
Intelligence Identities Protection Act,
which was enacted to prevent cases like
Philip Agi, not things like John
Kiryaku. It was to prevent the revealing
of covert identities for profit or to
aid the enemy. In this case, John
confirmed the name of a torturer
to a journalist. Um, which makes Neil
McBride's statement all the more
hypocritical because the biggest leaker
of classified information including
sources and methods and undercover
identities has been the US government.
>> John Kuryaku, explain what it is that
you were trying to expose. Explain what
you were involved with. Talk about Abu
Zuba, your involvement in the finding of
him and then the course you took. uh
where your conscience took you.
>> Sure. In in 2002, I was the chief of
counterterrorism operations uh for the
CIA in Pakistan and my job was to try to
locate al-Qaeda fighters or al-Qaeda
leaders and capture them to turn them
over to uh to the Justice Department and
um and have them face trial. That was
the original the original idea, not to
have them sit in Cuba for the next
decade. Uh but we we caught Abu Zabeda.
He was shot three times uh by Pakistani
uh police as he was trying to escape
from his safe house. And um and I was
the first person to uh to have custody
of him to sit with him. We spoke to each
other extensively. I mean talked about
everything from September 11th to poetry
that he had been writing to his family
and and then he was moved on to a secret
prison after that. Once I got back to
headquarters, um I heard that um he had
been subject to to harsh techniques uh
then euphemistically called enhanced
interrogation techniques. And I was
asked by uh one of the leaders in the
CIA's counterterrorist center if I
wanted to be trained in the use of these
techniques. I told him that I had a
moral problem with them and uh I did not
want to be involved. So u fast forward
to 2007.
By then um uh Human Rights Watch and
Amnesty International had reported that
al-Qaeda prisoners had been uh tortured
and ABC News called and said that they
had information that I had tortured Abu
Zuba. I said that was absolutely untrue.
I was the only person who was kind to
Abu Zuba and I had never tortured
anybody. So uh they asked me to go on
their show and defend myself. I did that
and in the course of the interview I
said that not only was the CIA torturing
prisoners but that it was official US
government policy. This was not the
result of some rogue CIA officer just
beating up a prisoner every once in a
while. This was official policy that
went all the way up to the president of
the United States.
>> And so what happened after that uh in
2007 once you gave this interview? Can
you explain what happened to you and and
to your family?
>> Sure. Within 24 hours, the CIA filed
what's called a crimes report against me
with the Justice Department, saying that
I had revealed classified information,
which was the torture program, and
asking for an investigation with an eye
toward prosecuting me. The Justice
Department decided at the time that I
had not revealed classified information,
that um the information was already in
the public domain. But um immediately,
within weeks, uh I was audited by the
IRS. I've been audited by the IRS every
single year since giving that interview
in 2007.
But a more important uh uh bit of
fallout from that interview was that
every time I would write an op-ed, every
time I would give a television interview
or give a speech at a university, the
CIA would file a crimes report against
me accusing me of leaking additional
classified information. Each time the
Justice Department determined that I did
not leak any classified information. In
fact, I would get those op-eds and those
speeches cleared by the CIA's
publications review board in advance.
Then the CIA started harassing my wife,
who at the time was a senior CIA
officer. Um, particularly over an op-ed
I had written. Uh, they accused her of
leaking classified information to me uh
for the purpose of writing the op-ed.
Well, I said I had gotten the
information in in the op-ed from two uh
UPI reports and from a uh South American
Ministry of Foreign Affairs website uh
and they would back off. But this this
sort of became our life. We would be
under FBI surveillance. She would be
called into the CIA's Office of
Security. Um I would have trouble uh
getting a security clearance when I went
to Capitol Hill. It just became this
pattern of harassment. So, John, why
didn't you stop?
>> Because I think that that torture is
something that needs to be discussed. I
said this in 2007. This is something
that we should about which we should be
having a national debate. And frankly, I
have a first amendment right to free
speech. And uh you know, writing an
op-ed is not against the law. Giving a
speech about the Arab Spring or about
torture is not against the law. And I
felt that that I didn't want to be
cowed. I didn't want to be frightened
into silence uh by the CIA.
>> And John Kiryako, you said that uh in
these instances that you've named, you
were actually charged with espionage. Is
that right? Can you talk about the
significance of the espionage act?
>> Yes. The government initially charged me
with three counts of espionage. Um,
I'm It sounds silly maybe, but I'm still
personally offended by these espionage
charges, which which were dropped. Of
course, the espionage charge is is used
as a hammer by the administration to
force people into silence. My espionage
charge is related to a conversation that
I had with a New York Times reporter. A
New York Times reporter approached me
and said that he was writing a story
about a colleague of mine. and uh would
I grant him an interview? I gave him the
interview. I said, "This colleague was a
great guy, the unsung hero of the Abu
Zuba operation, terrific officer." And
the reporter said, "Do you know how I
can get in touch with him?" And I said,
"No, I've been out of touch with him for
a while, but I think I might have his
business card." So, I gave the reporter
the business card. Now, mind you, this
is a CIA officer who had never ever been
undercover. his business card um showed
that he was involved as a CIA contractor
and it had his personal email on it and
his cell phone number. I gave the
reporter uh the business card and was
charged with two counts of espionage. I
later gave the same business card to
another journalist who was doing an
article and was charged with a third
count of espionage.
>> What is it that you allege the CIA was
doing for all of these years? explain
the torture program that you were trying
to expose.
>> Sure. There were there were something
like 10 different um techniques that
were used uh in the CIA's torture
program. They went from the benign um
you know uh where where an officer would
grab a prisoner by the lapels and and
give him a shake all the way up to the
really rough things that we've heard
about like water boarding or what I
think is worse uh sleep deprivation uh
or the cold cell where they'll put a
prisoner naked in a cell chilled to 50
or 55 degrees and then every hour or two
throw ice water on him. I I actually
think those last two are worse than
waterboarding. Um but again, the these
are techniques that we have condemned
other countries uh for throughout
history. The the Japanese did this
during the Second World War. Uh the
Belgians did it in in Africa uh earlier
in the century. Uh the Chinese and the
Vietnamese did it. This is these are
techniques that we have always said were
crimes against humanity. And then it was
though it was though after September
11th everything changed and we somehow
had license to do the same things we had
been condemning. I I thought that was
wrong. You know, Director Petraeus,
former director Petraeus made a
statement in October when I agreed to
take a plea to make these other charges
go away. Uh and he said u that my
conviction shows that we have to take
our oaths seriously. Well, I took my
oath seriously. My oath was to to the
Constitution. On my first day in the
CIA, I I put my right hand up and I
swore to uphold the Constitution. And to
me, torture is unconstitutional and it's
something that we should not be in the
business of doing.
>> Uh John Kyaku, I want to play for you
comments President Obama made four years
ago, shortly before he took office,
about whether CIA officials involved in
torture should be prosecuted. He
appeared on the ABC News this week. I
don't believe that anybody is above the
law. On the other hand, I also have a
belief that we need to look forward as
opposed to look looking backwards. Uh
and part of my job is to make sure that
for example at the CIA, uh you've got
extraordinarily talented people who are
working very hard to keep Americans
safe. Uh I don't want them to suddenly
feel like they've got to spend all their
time uh work looking over their
shoulders and and lawyering. No 9/11
commission with independent subpoena
power.
>> You know, we have not made final
decisions, but my instinct is for us to
focus on how do we make sure that moving
forward uh we are doing the right thing.
>> That was President Obama speaking four
years ago to ABC. Uh John Kuryaku, your
response to what the president said.
>> I supported uh uh the president's
response. I remember that interview and
and I thought, okay, he's right. There
are wonderful, talented, hardworking men
and women at the CIA who need to be
protected. But at the same time, it's
one thing to look forward. It's another
thing to look forward just for the
torturers. It's just not fair. It's not
fair to the American people. If we're
going to if we're going to make
prosecutions
or or initiate prosecutions, those
prosecutions can't just be against the
people who who blew the whistle on the
torture or who opposed to who opposed
the torture. Uh you know, we haven't we
haven't uh even investigated the
torturers. Uh, as Jesseline said, uh, we
haven't, um, initiated any actions
against the people who conceived of the
torture and implemented the policy or
against the man who destroyed evidence
of the torture or against the attorneys
who used specious legal arguments to
justify the torture. If we're going to
move forward, let's move forward. But
you can't target one person or two
people uh, who blew the whistle. Uh John
Kiraaku, you've also spoken about
witnessing new foreign service officers
being confirmed. Foreign services
officers who were previously with the
CIA and participated in acts of torture.
Could you explain what happened and
explain its significance?
>> Yes. When I was a a senior investigator
on the Senate Foreign Relations
Committee, I was approached by a
journalist who said that he had evidence
that the CIA was uh misusing its cover
agreement with the State Department to
place people involved in the torture
program under State Department cover so
that their names could not be exposed in
the press. And if those names were
exposed in the press, the the people
giving the names would be subject to the
Intelligence Identities Protection Act.
So, uh, again, this was a violation of
the, uh, of the CIA State Department
cover agreement. Uh, I sent a letter
under Senator John Kerry, then Senator
John K's, uh, signature asking the CIA
for clarification.
I got a response about six weeks later
that was classified top secret. So, I
was not permitted to to see the
response. I did not have a top secret
clearance at the time. And uh a
colleague of mine told me that the
letter essentially said in very strongly
worded language to mind my own business.
>> We're going to go to break and when we
come back we want to ask you about
President Obama's nominee to become the
next head of the CIA, John Brennan.
Because as you talk about the
administration, we're talking actually
about administrations from the Bush
administration to the Obama
administration. Our guest is about to go
to jail. His name is John Kuryaku. He's
about to serve two and a half years in
jail. these this will be one of his last
interviews where before he goes to
prison. We're joined also by Jocelyn
Raak who is one of his attorneys. Stay
with us.
Thanks so